<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Emily Sheehan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Shiny App</title>
      <link>/post/self-review/self-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/self-review/self-review/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;introducing-my-shiny-app&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introducing my Shiny App&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of my app is to enable users to develop insights on the state of Coronavirus in Australia through comparing data between chosen states over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My app is broken up into tabs to enhance its usability. There is an ‘About’ tab, a ‘How’ tab and an example tab detailing how I drew insights on Coronavirus using the app. This hopes to give the user a clear understanding on how to use the app, irrespective of their technological competence/capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘output’ tabs each contain a visualisation. The first has a map, the second has a line plot and the third has a comparison table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use the map, the user must input the states that they want to compare. It will generate a circle, and the size of the circle is dependent on the number of confirmed cases in that state to date. The user can click on the circle and it will give the exact number of confirmed cases in that state or territory. In the example below, I have chosen New South Wales and Victoria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/Self-review/map-nsw-vic.png&#34; /&gt;
The user must choose a case type in addition to the previously selected states or territories to use the plot. Therefore the confirmed, recovered or daily death toll between chosen states or territories can be compared overtime. To produce the plot below I have chosen ‘confirmed’ as my case type. The plot can be ‘double-clicked’ to reveal a timeline of COVID-19 related events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/Self-review/plot-nsw-vic.png&#34; /&gt;
Finally, to use the comparison table the user must select a date or dates to compare in addition to the previously selected states/territories and case type. This will generate a table which will allow them to compare daily case numbers and total case numbers for the chosen case type. dates and areas. I chose the earliest and most recent date to generate the comparison table below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/Self-review/comparison-nsw-vic.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;self-review&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Self Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-did-i-do-well&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What did I do well?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three aspects of the app that I did well were the user input and plotly event aspect of the app, as well as the explanation on how to use the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did the explanation aspect of the app well because I provided an example of how I derived insights and arrived at conclusions using the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plotly event that I created allows the user to ‘double-click’ on the plot to reveal a timeline of events, as mentioned above. I think I did this well because the user can easily compare and link the timeline events to points in the plot and draw conclusions on whether the restrictions were an effective measure in controlling the case numbers (as an example).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My use of the input data to generate outputs was well done because it meant the user has complete freedom in the outputs they want to generate as every output depends on the inputs they want to use. ??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-could-i-improve-on&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What could I improve on?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My comparison table could definitely be improved. For example, when ‘death’ is input the table and values change, however, the column headings are the same. In this context, the headings don’t make sense as they are titled ‘number of new cases’ and ‘total number of cases’. it would make more sense if they changed according to input and were titled ‘number of new deaths’ and ‘total number of deaths’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I coded the title of the plot so that it would change according to input. This means that if the user selects ‘confirmed’ the title would change to ‘The number of &lt;strong&gt;confirmed&lt;/strong&gt; COVID-19 cases’, and so on. However, when ‘death’ is selected the title changes to ‘The number of &lt;strong&gt;death&lt;/strong&gt; COVID-19 cases’. This doesn’t make gramatical sense, however, the &lt;code&gt;paste0&lt;/code&gt; function did not have the capacity to change the whole title based on the selected case type. In hindsight, I should have used an &lt;code&gt;ifelse&lt;/code&gt; statement to produce a better title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-plausible-addition-to-my-app&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A plausible addition to my app&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to update the map so that the circles change based on the case type chosen (as well as the states and/or territories chosen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main issue with this change is the map doesn’t delete circles if the input has been changed. For example, if I select New South Wales and Victoria, and then deselect Victoria, it won’t update the map. This means that if a case type is chosen and then changed, the map will layer the two case types which is problematic for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To overcome this problem, I have two approaches that I think would be feasible. The first would involve use the &lt;code&gt;ifelse&lt;/code&gt; function and the second improving the use of the reactive function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;an-implausible-addition-to-my-app&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;An implausible addition to my app&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;age group breakdown
whos spreading the virus
whos dying frm it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coronavirus in the UK</title>
      <link>/post/uk/coronavirus-in-the-uk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/uk/coronavirus-in-the-uk/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/pymjs/pym.v1.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/widgetframe-binding/widgetframe.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;the-first-wave&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The First Wave&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom had its first case of COVID-19 on the 31st of January, 2020. On the 1st of March, they had 6 cases. On the 7th of March, they had 55 cases. Two weeks later, they had 1215 cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early March, the Prime Minister was reluctant to ban mass gatherings as the modeling suggested it would have little benefit. Instead, the initial response was “based on science”, with Boris Johnson focusing on contact tracing and isolation of those exposed to COVID-19 (Hunter, 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/UK/2020-09-12-coronavirus-in-the-uk.en_files/figure-html/annotated-first-wave-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.K. Chief Scientist suggested herd immunity would be achieved if 60% or more of the population recovered from COVID-19 (Hunter, 2020). In this sense, the UK was striving towards attaining herd immunity while protecting the elderly and immunocompromised. A leading epidemiologist likened this approach to “a satire” (Hanage, 2020), as this would mean a high number of deaths and devastation across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 16, the UK shifted their public policy instructing citizens to avoid mass gatherings, work from home if possible, avoid non-essential travel and isolate if they had symptoms. On March 20, all pubs, all restaurants and most schools were closed. Approximately three weeks later the number of COVID-19 cases began to peak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-second-wave&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Second Wave&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of new COVID-19 cases have steadily increased since pubs and restaurants have re-opened. In addition, there has been an increase in illegal parties, which is leading to high levels of transmission among young people (Rosney, 2020). Although the daily case numbers are still considerably lower than April, the graph below is clearly trending upwards and the attitudes of civilians are becoming an increasing threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This considered, the UK are on the brink of a second wave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/UK/2020-09-12-coronavirus-in-the-uk.en_files/figure-html/annotated-second-wave-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;confirmed-covid-19-cases-in-the-uk-overtime&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Confirmed COVID-19 Cases in the UK Overtime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interactive display showing the confirmed number of COVID-19 cases in the UK since the 22nd of January, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;widgetframe html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;url&#34;:&#34;/post/UK/2020-09-12-coronavirus-in-the-uk.en_files/figure-html//widgets/widget_confirmed-plot.html&#34;,&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;xdomain&#34;:&#34;*&#34;,&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;:false,&#34;lazyload&#34;:false}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;confirmed-deaths-from-covid-19-in-the-uk-overtime&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Confirmed Deaths from COVID-19 in the UK Overtime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interactive display showing the number of COVID-19 deaths in the UK since the 22nd of January, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-2&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;widgetframe html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-2&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;url&#34;:&#34;/post/UK/2020-09-12-coronavirus-in-the-uk.en_files/figure-html//widgets/widget_death-plot.html&#34;,&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;xdomain&#34;:&#34;*&#34;,&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;:false,&#34;lazyload&#34;:false}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunter, D. J. (2020). Covid-19 and the stiff upper lip—The pandemic response in the United Kingdom. The New England Journal of Medicine. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp2005755&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp2005755&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanage, W. (2020). I’m an epidemiologist. When I heard about Britain’s ‘herd immunity’coronavirus plan, I thought it was satire. The Guardian, 03–15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rosney, D. (2020, September 7). Coronavirus: Young people breaking rules risk ‘second wave’. BBC. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/newsbeat-54056771&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.bbc.com/news/newsbeat-54056771&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coronavirus in Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>/post/saudi/coronavirus-in-saudi-arabia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/saudi/coronavirus-in-saudi-arabia/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/lightable/lightable.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/pymjs/pym.v1.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/widgetframe-binding/widgetframe.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;data-description&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus data comprises of 7 variables and over 175,000 observations for a number of countries. The variables include; date, province, country, latitude, longitude, type of case (i.e. confirmed/recovered) and number of daily cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The raw data has been collected on a daily basis since the 22nd of January 2020 by John Hopkins University Center for Systems Science and Engineering. The sources for the raw data include; the World Health Organisation, the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China, the European Center for Disease Prevention and Control, the U.S Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, local media reports, 1point3acres, Worldometers.info, BNO, DXY and other state and national government health departments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The raw data has been tidied and collated into a package titled &lt;em&gt;coronavirus&lt;/em&gt;, which has subsequently been used for this analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;an-explanation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An Explanation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus is the name given to a range of respiratory illnesses originating from the same family (Raoult et al., 2020). Each virus varies in its symptoms, with some strains being more fatal than others. Some of the viruses that belong to this family include; Middle Eastern Respiratory Syndrome (MERS-CoV), Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS-CoV) and COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-comparison&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Comparison&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since appearing in Saudi Arabia in 2012, MERS has spread to 27 countries resulting in a total of 2494 confirmed cases of MERS-CoV worldwide. Saudi Arabia was home to approximately 2102 infections, and had 780 deaths, resulting in a death rate of 37.11% (World Health Organisation, 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34; lightable-minimal&#34; style=&#39;font-family: &#34;Trebuchet MS&#34;, verdana, sans-serif; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#39;&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;tab:confirmed-table&#34;&gt;Table 1: &lt;/span&gt;Summary Statistics for New COVID-19 Cases in Saudi Arabia
&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Average New Cases per day
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Maximum Number of New Cases per day
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Total Number of Cases
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
1437.005
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
4919
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
275905
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since early 2020, there have been approximately 275905 cases of COVID-19 in Saudi Arabia and 2866, thus resulting in a death rate of 1.04%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34; lightable-minimal&#34; style=&#39;font-family: &#34;Trebuchet MS&#34;, verdana, sans-serif; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#39;&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;tab:death-table&#34;&gt;Table 2: &lt;/span&gt;Summary Statistics for Deaths due to COVID-19 in Saudi Arabia
&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Average Deaths per day
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Maximum Number of Deaths per day
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Total Number of Deaths
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
14.92708
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
58
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
2866
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maximum number of new cases on any given day was 4919 cases, which is approximately 234.02% of the total number of MERS-CoV infections in Saudi Arabia over an 8-year period, emphasizing the magnitude of COVID-19. The average number of new infections per day is approximately 1437 cases, whilst the average number of recovered cases per day is approximately 1227 cases. The maximum number of recovered cases on a given day was 7718 cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34; lightable-minimal&#34; style=&#39;font-family: &#34;Trebuchet MS&#34;, verdana, sans-serif; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#39;&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;tab:recovered-table&#34;&gt;Table 3: &lt;/span&gt;Summary Statistics for Recovered COVID-19 Cases in Saudi Arabia
&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Average Recovered Cases per day
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Maximum Number of Recovered Cases per day
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Total Number of Recovered Cases
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
1227.385
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
7718
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
235658
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the summary statistics and the interactive table suggest a clear difference in the prevalence of MERS-CoV and COVID-19. Although MERS-CoV is much more fatal with an alarmingly high death rate, COVID-19 is much more infectious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;widgetframe html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;url&#34;:&#34;/post/Saudi/2020-09-03-coronavirus-in-saudi-arabia.en_files/figure-html//widgets/widget_interactive-table-saudi.html&#34;,&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;xdomain&#34;:&#34;*&#34;,&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;:false,&#34;lazyload&#34;:false}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-09-03-coronavirus-in-saudi-arabia.en_files/featured.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bhaskar Karambelkar (2017). widgetframe: ‘Htmlwidgets’ in Responsive ‘iframes’. R package version 0.3.1.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=widgetframe&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=widgetframe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hao Zhu (2020). kableExtra: Construct Complex Table with ‘kable’ and Pipe Syntax. R package version 1.2.1.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=kableExtra&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=kableExtra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rami Krispin and Jarrett Byrnes (2020). coronavirus: The 2019 Novel Coronavirus COVID-19 (2019-nCoV) Dataset.
R package version 0.3.0.9000. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/RamiKrispin/coronavirus&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/RamiKrispin/coronavirus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raoult, D., Zumla, A., Locatelli, F., Ippolito, G., &amp;amp; Kroemer, G. (2020). Coronavirus infections: Epidemiological, clinical
and immunological features and hypotheses. Cell Stress &amp;amp; Chaperones, 4(4), 66–75.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wickham et al., (2019). Welcome to the tidyverse. Journal of Open Source Software, 4(43), 1686,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01686&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01686&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World Health Organisation. (2020, March 10). Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus
(MERS-CoV). Retrieved 4 September 2020, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.who.int/emergencies/mers-cov/en/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.who.int/emergencies/mers-cov/en/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
